Imagine that we have a cylinder.
A cylinder is a very simple, three-dimensional
object but imagine that we have two-dimensional
creatures trying to make sense of a cylinder.
It’s like the flatland conversation.
So two-dimensional creature intersects the
cylinder this way and they see a circle.
And in a two-dimensional world a circle is
a very clear object, makes perfect sense.
They can describe the mathematics of it.
And they can verify that empirically they
really did see a circle.
Of course a two-dimensional create that happens
to be in another plane could bisect the cylinder
like this and see a rectangle.
And they could be very clear on that also
and they’re both partially true but they’re
also both totally wrong in that rectangle
and circle are both two-dimensional objects
and the thing they’re encountering is a
three-dimensional object that actually can’t
be understood in the dimensionality that they’re
in.
So then we can see that a debate ensues between
the two-dimensional creatures in orthogonal
planes, the circlers and the rectanglers,
who are both utterly sure that the thing that
they’re seeing is what they think it is
and obviously rectangle and circle are mutually
exclusive descriptions of reality.
One has no corners and straight lines.
One is define exclusively by corners and straight
lines.
So it’s easy to see how one can hold a kind
of reductive fundamentalist perspective without
even thinking that it is that.
It’s just what I’m observing.
An so then they can debate.
Let’s imagine that one of the two-dimensional
creatures was able to switch planes and see
the other one and see that there was some
truth in both of them.
Then they could flip flop between perspectives
at different times or they could say we just
need to hold paradox.
It’s both and neither which mostly means
give up on making sense of reality.
Or they say it’s a middle path that’s
somewhere between the two.
And a middle path in two dimensions is like
a rounded rectangle where you kind of do something
that’s a little bit circle-ish and a little
bit rectangle-ish which isn’t even any true
part of what a cylinder is.
And the thing is that they’re just at too
low of a dimensional perspective to properly
understand the nature of cylinder which is
actually a very simple thing.
It doesn’t require holding paradox.
It doesn’t require a middle path in that
way.
And it’s because when we think of middle
path oftentimes we’re thinking of extremes
on left or right in a gradient.
But sometimes the two different perspectives
aren’t on a gradient on a single axis.
They’re orthogonal to each other.
And the reason why this is kind of actually
an interesting example is because perception
itself, a perspective on something defined
by perception is inherently a reduction of
information of the thing.
My perspective of it is going to be a lot
less total information than the actual thing
is.
So I can look at the object from the east
side or the west side or the top or the north
side or the inside, microscopically, telescopically.
They’ll all give me different information.
None will give me the entirety of the information
about the situation.
And so there is no all encompassing perspective
that gives me all of the information about
really almost any situation.
And so what this means is that reality itself
is trans perspectival.
It can’t be captured in any perspective.
So multiple perspectives have to be taken,
all of which will have some part of the reality,
some signal.
There may also be distortion.
I may be looking at the thing through a fisheye
lens or through a colored lens that creates
some distortion.
But then let’s say I’m looking at a building
and the picture, the 2D picture from the east
side and from the west side and from inside
a particular room and the aerial view are
all obviously very different pictures and
it’s because the 3D complex building actually
can’t be seen in a 2D process.
So I could take a lot of pictures and I could
seam them together into a kind of video that
moves through the building.
Now by having a video I added the dimension
of time and I got back to kind of the right
dimensionality to be able to understand the
thing.
But that’s not a perspective.
That’s a lot of perspectives that we’re
able to put together.
So why does this matter.
Well, when we’re looking at political processes
and we think about classically political left
kind of perspectives that have more to do
with the orientation of the collective and
the whole and political right that have more
to do with the individual and sovereignty.
On the right do we want people who are more
self-responsible and who are more sovereign
and who are more empowered.
And do we want to give more power to people
who are doing a better job.
All of that makes perfect sense.
Left perspective.
Do we want to create situations that actually
influence the individuals in the situation
to do better – social systems, education,
healthcare.
Does the environment affect the individual.
You can really think of it as does the environment
affect the individual while understanding
evolutionary theory that individuals are really
formed by their environment, of course.
With humans that are niche creators do the
individuals effect their environment.
Of course.
If you hold either of those as the only perspective
obviously you’re just missing so much which
is that the individual is affecting the whole.
The whole is, in turn affecting the individuals
and how do we create systems that have virtuous
cycles between empowering individuals and
creating better social systems that have the
effect of creating humans that are not dependent
on the social systems but that are more sovereign
and can, in turn, create better social systems.
And whether we’re thinking about a political
issue like that or we’re looking at a psychologic
issue like the orientation of being and enjoying
reality as is and accepting ourselves and
others as is and doing and becoming which
is adding to life, adding to ourselves, seeking
to improve ourselves.
How do we hold these together.
They don’t just have to be held as paradox
or holding one or flip flopping.
There’s a way that when understanding how
they relate to each other – so in that example
if I understand the nature of a person as
a noun that is static then it seems like accepting
them the way they are unconditionally, removes
the basis for growth.
But if I understand that the person is a dynamic
process, that they’re actually a verb that
intrinsic to what they are in the moment is
desire and impulse to grow and become.
And like that loving someone unconditionally
involves wanting for them their own self-actualization
and there’s no dichotomy between accepting
someone ourselves as is or the world and seeking
to help it grow, advance, express.
So it’s a very simple process of saying
the ability to take multiple perspectives,
to see the partial truth in them and then
to be able to seam them together into something
that isn’t a perspective.
It’s a trans perspective capacity to hold
the relationships between many perspectives
in a way that can inform our choice-making
is fundamental to navigating reality.